In atomic physics, the Electron Shell Model
describes the distribution of electrons on
the »energy shells« of an atom in the periodic
table of elements.
For example, it can be used to understand
the electron distribution of an oxygen atom.
We can see from the periodic table that an
oxygen atom has 8 electrons.
But how are they distributed in the atom?
The shell model answers this question.
Each shell represents a certain energy.
The electrons can occupy these shells and
thus take on this energy.
Each shell can only hold a certain number
of electrons.
The electrons on the outermost shell of an
atom are known as valence electrons and they
play a crucial role in chemical reactions.
The shells are labeled with letters: The innermost
(first) shell is called the K-shell.
It can hold a maximum of 2 electrons.
Then it is completely filled.
The second shell is called the L-shell.
It can hold a maximum of 8 electrons.
The third shell is called the M shell.
It can hold a maximum of 18 electrons.
The fourth shell is called the N-shell.
It can hold a maximum of 32 electrons.
How do I know the maximum number of electrons
a shell can hold?
There is a formula for this.
Let's call the maximum number of electrons
that a shell can hold as "n_max".
You can then calculate this number using the
following formula: "n_max" is equal to two
n squared.
Where "n" is the shell number.
For the first shell, the K shell, "n equals
one".
For the second shell, the L-shell, "n equals
two" For the third shell, the M-shell, "n
equals three", and so on!
Let's take a look at four examples.
First, the hydrogen atom.
If you look at the periodic table, you can
read the number of electrons from the atomic
number in the corner.
The hydrogen atom has an atomic number of
one.
This means it only has one electron.
We start with the innermost shell, the K shell,
and add an electron to it.
As the hydrogen atom has no other electrons,
it only has a half-filled K-shell.
The lithium atom has the atomic number three.
This means it has three electrons.
We start with the K shell.
The K-shell can hold two electrons, so we
fill it with two electrons.
The third electron is added to the next shell,
the L shell.
The oxygen atom has eight electrons.
Two are on the K shell.
The L-shell can hold a maximum of eight electrons,
so the remaining six electrons are added to
it.
The aluminum atom has thirteen electrons.
Two electrons are added to the K-shell.
Eight electrons are added to the L-shell,
then the K-shell is full.
The remaining three electrons are added to
the M-shell.